Finding Aid for Michigan Union Records 1884-
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Union records 1884-[ongoing], 1904-1995
Michigan Union.
1 oversize folders
13 oversize volumes
23 linear feet
University of Michigan student organization formed to build and manage a student union, sponsors a variety of social and service programs and activities, includes records of building and financial committees and various activity/organization files including the University Mimes and the Union Opera (later renamed MUSKET) and scrapbooks and photographs of Union activities.
87241 BImu Bimu F15 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records of the Michigan Union ( Donor no. 2024 ) were first received in 1944; additional accessions are received on a periodic basis.
The collection is open for research.
The idea of an organization embracing all of the University of Michigan's male students was offered by Edward F. Parker in the fall of 1903. The proposal sprang from a concern that a divisiveness was growing among the students, particularly between the fraternity members and the "independents," that is non-fraternity members. Parker's proposal was supported at the highest levels within the university, including the president and several deans. In February 1904 the first organizational meeting was held and the name Michigan Union was chosen. In June, 1904 articles of association were signed, establishing the Michigan Union as an organization embracing all male students, alumni, faculty and regents. Although considered a part of the university family, the Michigan Union was legally a separate entity responsible only to its own Board of Directors.
Almost immediately fund raising began for the construction of a building. Because of competing university projects early fund raising efforts were not particularly successful, but in 1907 sufficient funds had been obtained to purchase the home of Thomas M. Cooley on State Street to serve as headquarters for the organization. The Cooley home was seen as a temporary location, and plans for a new building, as well as fund raising efforts, continued. In 1908, as a part of this ongoing fund raising, the Union instituted one of its longest traditions, the Michigan Union Opera. The all-male opera toured in the fall, and occasionally the spring, visiting cities with strong alumni clubs.
Years of fund raising were rewarded in 1916 when construction began on the Cooley site of a new Union Building. Sufficient funds existed, however, only to erect the outer shell of the structure. The first interior work was performed with funds loaned by the Michigan State War Preparedness Board, which wished to use the building as a barracks for soldiers of the Students Army Training Corps (SATC) who were sent to Ann Arbor for training. In 1918 more money was borrowed, and although several key components of the structure were still left unfinished due to a lack of funds, the building was opened for the use of members in the fall of 1919.
The continuing financial problems of the Union led its governing board to seek the aid of the Regents. While membership in the Union was open to all male students, membership, and the payment of dues, was voluntary. In academic year 1918-1919 the Regents made the payment of Union dues a part of the registration fees paid automatically by enrolled students. This assistance in funding the union occurred at a time when the Union was reordering its financial operations to reflect the large, multifaceted building it now operated. In 1917 a separate Board of Governors was authorized by the Board of Directors to oversee the Union's financial operation. This body did not actually begin to operate until 1920, and in 1928 it was abolished and replaced by a Finance Committee of the Board of Directors.
The Union's basic functions continued undisturbed throughout the 1930s, although the building itself was expanded with additions constructed in 1936 and 1938. The influx of students after World War II strained the physical capacities, but more important were a series of social changes that challenged the Union's status as an all male club. Barriers to the participation of women in Union events were slowly, and sometimes painfully, dropped. In 1956 unescorted women were first allowed into the union. In the same year the all male Union Opera allowed women to participate in its production, changing its name to MUSKET--Michigan Union Show, Ko-Eds Too. Barriers continued to fall throughout the 1960s until the last vestige of the Union's exclusively male character, a clause barring women from life membership in the Union, was dropped in 1972.
The Union's unique governmental status was abandoned in 1979, when the Union came under the control of the Vice-President for Student Services.
The records of the Michigan Union measure 21 linear feet and 13 oversize volumes. The records date from 1890 to 1983, although there are some collected photographs dating as early as 1884. The collection has been divided into six series: Central Files, Activity/Organization Files, General Files, Photographs, Songs, and Board of Representatives.
Subjects:
Michigan Union.; Michigan Union Opera.; Mimes (University of Michigan); Musket (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Allen, Hugh Pitzer, 1882-; Allen, John Robins, 1869-1920.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Barkdull, Howard L., 1887-; Baxter, Kenneth Stewart, 1883-; Bisbee, Leland S.; Blain, D. Bethune, 1879-1963.; Buckley, L. Paul.; Bulkley, Harry C. (Harry Conant), b. 1870.; Bursley, Joseph Aldrich, 1877-1950.; Cheever Court (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Chequamegon Band & Orchestra.; Clark, Herbert Watson.; Comedy Club (University of Michigan); Construction industry.; Druids (University of Michigan); Jefferson Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Dickinson, Seldon, 1892-1964.; Douglass, Henry Woolsey.; Friedman, Louis Kossuth, 1894-; Gault, Harry G., 1892-; Haislip, Edward Watson, 1886-1965.; Heath, Homer L.; Helsell, Frank Pritchard, 1886-1966.; Jones, Paul, 1880-1941.; Kirk, Richard Ray, 1877-; Knapp, Burton Samuel, 1882-1959.; Koontz, Patrick Duffey, 1888-1947.; McKenzie, William Dexter, 1873-1960.; Maxwell, Lawrence, 1853-1927.; Merritt, Walle Williard, 1884-1968.; Michigamua.; Michigan Union.; Michigan Union Opera.; Millen, George W., b. 1863.; Parades.; Quadrangle Club (University of Michigan); Peterson, Reuben, 1862-1942.; Riggs, Henry Earle, 1865-1949.; Roberts, Thomas Brockway.; Saier, Edward Herbert.; Sealby, Inman, 1862-; Sports.; Sphinx (Fraternity: University of Michigan); Stevens, Frederick W. (Frederick Waeir), 1865-1926.; Thomason, Samuel Emory, 1883-1944.; Thompson Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Triangles (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Baseball.; University of Michigan--Basketball.; University of Michigan--Crew.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan. Men's Glee Club.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1881-1890.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Track athletics.; Wagner, Frank Caspar, 1864-1928.; Watkins, James K., 1887-; West Quadrangle (University of Michigan); Zane, John Maxcy, 1863-1937.
Genre/Form:
Scrapbooks.; Photographs.; Lantern slides.; Slides.
- Central Files 1904-circa 1979
  Central Files (1904-ca. 1979) have been further divided into three subseries, Board of Directors, Committees, and Union Presidents. The Board of Directors material is most notable for a complete set of Board minutes (1904-1979). Committee records are most interesting for the records of the Finance Committee, which includes records of the committee's predecessor, the Board of Governors. Included are minutes (1920-1963), annual audits (1914-1960) and monthly financial statements (1919-1960). Union Presidents material consists of correspondence from two early union presidents, Edward G. Kemp (correspondence dates 1905; 1911-1913) and Seldon S. Dickinson (correspondence dates 1913-1914).
  - Board of Directors
    - Constitutions 1907-1956 (Box 1)
    - By-laws
      - 1967 (Box 1)
      - 1976 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings
      - February 1904-1957, 8 volumes (Box 1)
      - 1957-1979, 4 folders; 4 volumes (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1 folders (Box 3)
  - Committees
    - Building
      - 1911-1917 (Box 3)
      - 1936 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence with Irving Pond 1924-1938 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous 1919-1979, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Bylaws Revision 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - Financial
      - Minutes (Box 3)
      - Annual Audit
        - 1914-1920, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - 1920-1961, 9 folders (Box 4)
      - Monthly Financial Statement
        - 1919-1927, 2 folders; 6 volumes (Box 4)
        - 1928-1942, 15 folders (Box 5)
        - 1943-1960, 18 folders (Box 6)
        - 1964, 8 folders (Box 6)
      - Building Fund Campaign 1911-1926 (Box 7)
        - 1911-1926, 20 folders; 1 volumes (Box 7)
        - 1911-1926, 4 folders; 1 volumes (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous, including Property Records and Mortgages, 6 folders (Box 8)
      - Space Allocation 1970-1972, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Union-League Joint Conference and Merger 1970-1971
        - Merger Discussions circa 1967 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence of Union Presidents
    - 1905, 1911-1913 (Edward G. Kemp) (Box 8)
    - 1913-1914 (Seldon S. Dickinson) (Box 8)
    - 1914-1915 (Patrick D. Koontz) (Box 8)
- Activity/Organization Files 1908-1972
  Activity/Organization Files includes information about activities sponsored by the Union or organizations which had offices in the Union. The largest body of material documents the Union Opera/MUSKET. Generally this is material regarding the annual productions (1908-1962). There are also folders on the Rainbow People's Party (1971-1972) and Students for a Democratic Society (1965-1968), although information about these groups is not particularly incisive. Material on opera productions appears in a variety of formats and sizes. Scores and programs are separately described in the printed material subgroup, and opera material also is included in the Songs and Photographs series.
  - Anniversary of Union Celebrations
    - 50th 1954 (Box 9)
    - 60th 1964 (Box 9)
  - Mimes
    - Minutes 1912-1927 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Office of Special Services and Programs
    - Annual Report 1972/73 (Box 9)
    - Budget Request 1973/74 (Box 9)
  - Opera/MUSKET
    - Minnie Mae Root Correspondence 1913-1941 n.d. (Box 9)
    - Minutes 1954-1955 (Box 9)
    - Opera Sheet Music Sales Books 1908-1913, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Study Committee 1949-1955 (Box 9)
    - Try Out Cards 1940 (Box 9)
      (includes card for Tom Harmon)
    - Productions
      (see also Photographs, Songs, and Printed Material)
      - Undated
        - The Hottentot (Box 9)
      - 1908
        - Michigenda (Box 9)
        - Culture, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1909
        - Koanzaland, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1910
        - The Crimson Chest (Box 9)
      - 1911
        - The Awakened Ramses, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1913
        - Contrarie Mary (Box 9)
      - 1914
        - A Model Daughter, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - 1915
        - All That Glitters, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - 1916
        - Tres Rouge, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - 1917
        - Fool's Paradise, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - 1918
        - Let's Go, Over Here, Over There, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - 1919
        - Come on Dad, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - 1920
        - George Did It, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - 1921
        - Top O' the Mornin' (Box 11)
        - Make it for Two (Box 11)
      - 1922
        - In and Out, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - 1923
        - Cotton Stockings (Box 11)
      - 1924
        - Tickled to Death (Box 11)
      - 1925
        - Tambourine (Box 11)
      - 1926
        - Front Page Stuff, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - 1927
        - The Same to You (Box 11)
      - 1928
        - Rainbow's End (Box 11)
      - 1929
        - Merrie-Go-Round (Box 11)
      - 1934
        - Aw Nuts! (Box 11)
        - With Banner's Flying (Box 11)
      - 1935
        - Give Us Rhythm (Box 12)
      - 1940
        - Four Out of Five (Box 12)
      - 1941
        - Take a Number (Box 12)
      - 1942
        - Full House (Box 12)
      - 1949
        - Froggy Bottom (Box 12)
      - 1950
        - Lace It Up, 5 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 12)
          (Located Separately in Stacks; no manuscript material)
      - 1951
        - Go West Madam, 4 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 12)
          (Located Separately in Stacks)
      - 1952
        - No Cover Charge (Box 12)
          (33 1/3 rpm Phonograph Record Located Separately in Stacks)
        - Never Too Late (Box 12)
      - 1953
        - Up and Atom (Box 12)
      - 1954
        - Hail to Victor (Box 12)
      - 1955
        - Flim-Flam (Box 12)
      - 1956
        - Brigadoon (Box 12)
      - 1957
        - Kiss Me Kate (Box 12)
      - 1958
        - Oklahoma (Box 12)
      - 1959
        - Carousel (Box 12)
      - 1960
        - Kismet (Box 12)
      - 1961
        - Land Ho! (Box 12)
          (33 1/3 rpm Phonograph Record Located Separately in Stacks; no manuscript material)
      - 1962
        - Bartholomew Fair (Box 12)
      - 1967
        - Out of Our Minds (Box 12)
          (33 1/3 rpm Phonograph Record Located Separately in Stacks, no manuscript material)
      - 1969
        - Camelot (Box 12)
      - 1971
        - My Fair Lady (Box 12)
          (Portraits)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Project Community/Trotter House
    - Budget
      - 1972/73 (Box 12)
      - 1973/74 (Box 12)
  - Rainbow People's Party 1971-1972 (Box 12)
  - Students for a Democratic Society 1965-1968 (Box 12)
  - Union Fair Scrapbook circa 1905 (Box 12)
  - University Club Minute Book 1890-1891 (Box 12)
  - WCBN 1962-1970 (Box 12)
- General Files 1890-1983
  General Files date from 1890-1983 and includes a small remnant of the Union's voluminous correspondence (1900-ca. 1959). Certain types of correspondence, such as room reservations, the desk manager's lost and found, Union membership dues and pins, ticket requests, and uncollectable checks were discarded. Also found in the General Files is a quantity of miscellaneous material. Although poorly described, the material can be of great interest. Included is correspondence with several university presidents as well as important individuals in the founding of the Union.
  - Correspondence and Other Documents
    - 1900-1922 (Box 13)
    - 1923-circa 1959 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
    (continued)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
- Photographs, 1885-circa 1970
  The photographs series Photographs consists of images of the Michigan Union building and the Michigan Union Opera productions, as well as collected photographs relating to life on the University of Michigan campus. Of note is a collection of team portraits of the various U-M athletic teams from the mid-1880s to the late 1920s. This collection of photographs should be supplemented with other athletic photographs in the library's holdings.
  - Photo Prints
    - Activities-general (Box 17)
    - Ann Arbor views (Box 17)
    - Building-exteriors (Box 17)
    - Building-interiors (Box 17)
    - Building-interior-Founder's Room (Box 17)
    - Campus buildings and views (Box 17)
    - Chequamegon Orchestra 1888 (Box 17)
    - Football, track, crew (Box 17)
    - Groups
      - Druids, 3 folders (Box 17)
      - Michigamua, Quadrangle, Sphinx, Triangles (Box 17)
      - Sigma Alpha Epsilon (Box 17)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
    - Individuals
      - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
      - Michigan Union Officers
        - Allen, Hugh P (Box 17)
        - Allen, John R (Box 17)
        - Barkdull, Howard L (Box 17)
        - Baxter, Kenneth S (Box 17)
        - Bisbee, Leland S (Box 17)
        - Blain, D. Bethune (Box 17)
        - Buckley, L. Paul (Box 17)
        - Bulkley, Harry (Box 17)
        - Bursley, Joseph (Box 17)
        - Clark, Herbert W (Box 17)
        - Dickinson, Seldon (Box 17)
        - Douglass, Henry W (Box 17)
        - Elbel, Louis (Box 17)
        - Friedman, Louis K (Box 17)
        - Gault, Harry G (Box 17)
        - Haislip, Edward W (Box 17)
        - Heath, Homer (Box 17)
        - Helsell, Frank P (Box 17)
        - Jones, Paul (Box 17)
        - Kirk, Richard R (Box 17)
        - Knapp, Burton S (Box 17)
        - Koontz, Patrick D (Box 17)
        - McKenzie, William D (Box 17)
        - Maxwell, Lawrence (Box 17)
        - Merritt, Walle W (Box 17)
        - Millen, George W (Box 17)
        - Parker, Edward F (Box 17)
        - Peterson, Reuben (Box 17)
        - Riggs, Henry E (Box 17)
        - Roberts, Thomas B (Box 17)
        - Saier, Edward H (Box 17)
        - Sealby, Inman (Box 17)
        - Snow, Neil (Box 17)
        - Stevens, Frederick W (Box 17)
        - Thomason, Samuel E (Box 17)
        - Wagner, Frank C (Box 17)
        - Watkins, James K (Box 17)
        - Zane, John M (Box 17)
        - 1993 accession (A-Z) (Box 17)
    - Michigan Union Opera productions (by date)
      - Michigenda (February 1908) (also oversize in box 21) (Box 17)
      - Culture (December 1908) (also oversize box 21) (Box 17)
      - Koanzaland (December 1909) (in oversize box 21, and outsize folder UBImul/F15) (Box 17)
      - The Crimson Chest (December 1910) (also in oversize box 21) (Box 17)
      - The Awakened Ramses (December 1911) (in oversize box 21) (Box 17)
      - Contrarie Mary (March 1913) (in oversize box 21) (Box 17)
      - A Model Daughter (March 1914) (also in oversize box 21) (Box 17)
      - All that Glitters (March 1915) (Box 17)
      - Tres Rouge (March 1916) (Box 17)
      - Fool's Paradise (March 1917) (Box 17)
      - Let's Go (1918) (Box 17)
      - Come on Dad (1919) (also in oversize box 21) (Box 17)
      - Top O' the Mornin' (March 1921) (also in oversize box 21) (Box 17)
      - In and Out (1922) (Box 17)
      - Tambourine (December 1925) (See Also Outsize Folder UBImul/F15) (Box 17)
      - Front Page Stuff (1926) (Box 17)
      - Same To You (1927) (Box 17)
      - Rainbow's End (1928) (Box 17)
      - With Banners Flying (April 1934); and Give Us Rhythm (December 1934) (Box 17)
      - Take A Number (1941) (Box 17)
      - Froggy Bottom, 1949 (Box 17)
    - Michigan Union Opera-miscellaneous or unidentified
      - Lionel Ames circa 1920 (Box 17)
        (also in oversize box 21)
      - Costume Design (Box 17)
        Sketches (in oversize box 21)
      - Stone family circa 1920 (Box 17)
      - Unidentified operas and individuals 1908-1952, 7 folders (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
    - Parades (Box 17)
    - Souvenir booklet photos (on masonite), 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Student activities (Box 17)
    - Negatives (Box 17)
    - Album showing construction of West Quadrangle Dormitory 1938-1939 (Box 17)
      (includes exterior and interior views of houses on the site)
  - Lantern slides
    - Exterior and interior sketches and photos of Union building, cartoons and photos of faculty members, and photos of university buildings, 1 boxes (Box 18)
    - Football and student activities, 2 boxes (Box 18)
  - Oversize photographs
    - Baseball Team Portraits 1892-1921 (Box 19)
    - Basketball Team Portraits 1918-1921 (Box 19)
    - Football Team Portraits 1884-1929, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Track Team Portraits 1896-1926 (Box 20)
      (with some action photos)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
      (include Michigamua, Quadrangle, Comedy Club, Men's Glee Club, Union Opera, WW I S.A.T.C.)
    - Michigan Union Officers and U-M faculty, 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Michigan Union Opera Productions (by date)
      (See Also Box 17)
      - Michigenda, February 1908 (Box 21)
      - Culture, December 1908 (Box 21)
      - Koanzaland, December 1909 (Box 21)
        (See also Outsize folder UBImul/F15)
      - The Crimson Chest, December 1910 (Box 21)
      - The Awakened Ramses, December 1911 (Box 21)
      - Contrarie Mary, March 1913 (Box 21)
      - A Model Daughter, March 1914 (Box 21)
      - Come on Dad, 1919 (Box 21)
      - Top O' The Mornin', 1921 (Box 21)
      - Tickled To Death, 1924 (Box 21)
      - Ames, Lionel circa 1920 (Box 21)
      - Costume Design Sketches circa 1920s (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous (including Union Opera (Folder UBImul F15)
      (1 folder in outsize location; call no. UBImul/F15)
    - Michigan Union Opera productions
      - Koanzaland 1909
    - Bands
      - Concert Band 1931 (Folder UBImul F15)
      - R.O.T.C. Band 1929 (Folder UBImul F15)
      - R.O.T.C. Band 1933 (Folder UBImul F15)
    - Opera Company
      - Opera Company from "Cotton Stockings" at the White House 1923 (Folder UBImul F15)
      - Opera Company from "Tambourine" at the White House 1925 (Folder UBImul F15)
      - Opera Company at Mount Vernon 1926 (Folder UBImul F15)
- Songs
  Songs consists of 78 rpm and 33 1/3 rpm phonograph records and manuscript sheet music for various Union Opera productions and assorted band arrangements. This series includes manuscripts for "Victors March" by Earl V. Moore.
  - Sheet Music Manuscripts
    - Awakened Ramses 1911 (Box 21)
    - Contrarie Mary 1913 (Box 21)
    - Crimson Chest 1910 (Box 21)
    - Crimson Chest and Ramses Medley (Box 21)
    - Culture 1908 (Box 21)
    - "Hail Michigan," by Cladius Pendill (Box 21)
    - "Here's to the S.A.T.C." by Tom Lovell 1918 (Box 21)
    - Junior Girls Play circa 1911-1915 (Box 21)
    - "Michigan's Men of Steel" (Parts for Band) (Box 21)
    - Michigenda 1908 (Box 21)
    - Michigenda and Culture 1908 (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
    - Earl V. Moore Arrangements (Box 21)
    - Ruth Smith Arrangements (Box 21)
    - "U of M Field Song" by William Whedon, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - "Varsity March," by Earl V. Moore, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - "Yellow and Blue," (Box 21)
  - Audio Recordings
    (78 rpm phonograph recordings located separately in stacks)
    - Ann Arbor Days, 2 phonograph records (Box 23)
    - College Days (Box 23)
    - The Victor's March (Box 23)
    - When Night Falls Dear, 2 phonograph records (Box 23)
    - The Yellow and the Blue (Box 21)
    - My Fair Lady 1971 (Box 23)
- Bound Volumes, 13 oversize volumes
  - Scrapbooks
    - October 1912-June 1922 (Folder BImu F15)
    - July 1922-April 1926 (Folder BImu F15)
    - May 1926-January 1929 (Folder BImu F15)
    - January 1929-May 17, 1931 (Folder BImu F15)
    - May 19, 1931-December 1933 (Folder BImu F15)
    - January 1934-October 1935 (Folder BImu F15)
    - November 1935-January 1938 (Folder BImu F15)
    - January 1938-April 1942 (Folder BImu F15)
    - July 1942-May 1948 (Folder BImu F15)
    - 1948-May 1952 (Folder BImu F15)
    - 1962-1963 (Folder BImu F15)
    - September 1977-May 1979 (Volume 1)
      (Special location: B 283 3)
  - Guest Register 1935-1943 (Volume 2)
    (not hotel register) (B 283 3)